<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Article Authoring DTD v1.0 20120330//EN"
  "JATS-articleauthoring1.dtd">
<article dtd-version="1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <front>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>An oXygen framework for Literatum JATS</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib>
          <name>
            <surname>Piez</surname>
            <given-names>Wendell</given-names>
          </name>
          <aff>Piez Consulting Services,
            <uri>http://www.wendellpiez.org/</uri></aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib>
          <name>
            <surname>Imsieke</surname>
            <given-names>Gerrit</given-names>
          </name>
          <aff>le-tex publishing services,
            <uri>http://www.le-tex.de/</uri></aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <abstract>
        <p>This is an adaptation of Wendell’s original oXygen XML Editor framework for JATS.
        It provides additional Checks for compliance with the submission guidelines for 
        Atypon’s Literatum platform. In addition, it provides a transformation scenario that
        generates JATS XML from legacy APA contentItem articles, and an XProc script to 
        create a Literatum submission Zip file from a file system directory of articles.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>JATS, the journal article tag suite, serves as a basis for Atypon’s Literatum content delivery platform. Articles may be
      delivered according to version 1.0 of the JATS archiving (“green”) DTD.</p>
    <p>A typical delivery to Literatum consists of all articles that belong to a given journal issue. In order to describe the
      contents of an issue, Atypon has added a lightweight issue-xml DTD that utilizes JATS vocabulary where available. In
      addition to blank templates for journal articles, this framework also contains a template for issue XML. Issue XML files
      may be saved alongside the articles that form an issue. A transformation scenario 'build-issue' will then collect all
      articles in that directory.</p>
    <p>There are Schematron checks for both article and issue XML that help content workers comply with Atypon’s requirements,
      such as naming or tagging conventions.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>Preview stylesheets and transformations</title>
      <p>Preview stylesheets capable of rendering Publishing (blue) and Authoring (orange) articles are included from
          <ext-link>https://github.com/NCBITools/JATSPreviewStylesheets</ext-link>. They are designed for local customization
        and extension, and include many options, as described in their documentation.</p>
      <sec>
        <title>Transformations generating HTML</title>
        <p>HTML files resulting from running these scenarios will point to a CSS file here (distributed with the
          XSLT):<preformat>${frameworks}/jats/jats-preview-xslt/jats-preview.css</preformat></p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Transformations generating PDF</title>
        <p>The Preview stylesheets also include XSL-FO stylesheets for generating PDF. These require a capable XSL-FO formatting
          engine (they were tested with AntennaHouse). So they are left for local users to set up.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Submission Package Builder</title>
      <p>There is an XProc transformation scenario 'build-issue' that operates on an issue-xml file, collects all JATS articles
        in the same directory and assembles them to a Literatum submission Zip file. This is currently a prototype and needs
        further development.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Document templates</title>
      <p>Document templates are provided only for the Archiving (green) document type, using the HTML table model.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Extending the framework</title>
      <p>Local developers may wish to do any or all of the following, extending the customization that this Literatum JATS framework already contains:<list>
          <list-item>
            <p>Rewrite the parameter setting in the HTML Transformation Scenario to point to a local (customized) CSS.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Provide transformation scenarios for any of the JATS Preview transformations or production pipelines given in the
              package, or for customized transformations.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Provide templates using the JATS DTDs supporting OASIS tables instead of or in addition to the templates
              here.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list></p>
      <p>In addition, there are many enhancements possible to this framework, including (but not limited to)<list>
          <list-item>
            <p>More and better CSS.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Custom actions, tools and buttons in oXygen for operations useful in writing and editing JATS documents, such as
              graphics, list and table support.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>If you make such extensions, please consider sharing them with the community!</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
</article>
