<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN"
  "JATS-articleauthoring1.dtd">
<article dtd-version="1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <front>
    <article-meta>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>An oXygen Framework for JATS 1.0</article-title>
        <subtitle>With package building support for Atypon’s Literatum platform 
          and extensive content checking rules</subtitle>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Imsieke</surname>
            <given-names>Gerrit</given-names>
          </name>
          <aff>le-tex publishing services,
            <uri>http://www.le-tex.de/</uri></aff>
        </contrib>
        <contrib>
          <name>
            <surname>Piez</surname>
            <given-names>Wendell</given-names>
          </name>
          <aff>Piez Consulting Services,
            <uri>http://www.wendellpiez.org/</uri></aff>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <abstract>
        <p>This is an adaptation of Wendell’s original oXygen XML Editor framework for JATS.
        It provides additional Checks for compliance with the submission guidelines for 
        Atypon’s Literatum platform. In addition, it provides a transformation scenario that
        generates JATS XML from legacy APA contentItem articles, and an XProc script to 
        create a Literatum submission Zip file from a file system directory of articles.</p>
      </abstract>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>JATS, the journal article tag suite, serves as a basis for Atypon’s Literatum content delivery platform. Articles may be
      delivered according to version 1.0 of the JATS archiving (“green”) DTD. Please consult Atypon’s Literatum Content Tagging Guide&#xa0;[<xref rid="bib-lctg" ref-type="bibr"/>].</p>
    <p>A typical delivery to Literatum consists of all articles that belong to a given journal issue. In order to describe the
      contents of an issue, Atypon has added a lightweight issue-xml DTD that utilizes JATS vocabulary where available. In
      addition to blank templates for journal articles, this framework also contains a template for issue XML. Issue XML files
      may be saved alongside the articles that form an issue. A transformation scenario 'build-issue' will then collect all
      articles in that directory.</p>
    <p>There are Schematron checks for both article and issue XML that help content workers comply with Atypon’s requirements,
      such as naming or tagging conventions.</p>
    <sec>
      <title>Preview stylesheets and transformations</title>
      <p>Preview stylesheets capable of rendering Publishing (blue) and Authoring (orange) articles are included from
          <ext-link>https://github.com/NCBITools/JATSPreviewStylesheets</ext-link>. They are designed for local customization
        and extension, and include many options, as described in their documentation.</p>
      <p>Please note that the documents that may be created and checked with this Literatum framework are essentially Archiving
        (green) JATS documents. Archiving is the richest of all JATS frameworks. Some elements may not be rendered properly.</p>
      <sec>
        <title>Transformations generating HTML</title>
        <p>HTML files resulting from running these scenarios will point to a CSS file here (distributed with the
          XSLT):<preformat>${frameworks}/jats/jats-preview-xslt/jats-preview.css</preformat></p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Transformations generating PDF</title>
        <p>The Preview stylesheets also include XSL-FO stylesheets for generating PDF. These require a capable XSL-FO formatting
          engine (they were tested with AntennaHouse). So they are left for local users to set up.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Submission Package Builder</title>
      <p>There is an XProc transformation scenario 'build-issue' that operates on an issue-xml file, collects all JATS articles
        in the same directory and assembles them to a Literatum submission Zip file. This is currently a prototype and needs
        further development.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Document templates</title>
      <p>Document templates are provided only for the Archiving (green) document type, using the HTML table model.</p>
    </sec>

    <sec>
      <title>Installating the Framework</title>
      <p>In oXygen 16, go to “Help &gt; Install new add-ons…” as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-01-install"/>.</p>
      <fig id="fig-01-install">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Menu item “Help &gt; Install new add-ons…” in oXygen 16.1</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="img/01-install.jpg"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Enter the update URL <uri>https://hobots.hogrefe.com/oXygenJATSframework_Literatum/oXygenJATSframework_Literatum.xml</uri>.
      The most recent version (not necessarily v0.2 as depicted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-02-install"/>) of the framework will 
        be offered for installation.</p>
      <fig id="fig-02-install">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Entering the update URL in oXygen 16.1’s “Install Add-ons” dialog</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="img/02-install.jpg"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Please note that oXygen version prior to 15.0 are currently not supported. If there is demand, we might be looking into
      supporting 14.x versions.</p>
      <fig id="fig-03-install">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Warning: Package is not digitally signed</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="img/03-install.jpg"/>
      </fig>
      <p>The package is not digitally signed. We might sign it at a later stage. If you trust the people who control the server
        providing the download link, chances are high that the package hasn’t been tampered with. So press “Continue anyway”
          (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-03-install"/>)</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Using the Framework</title>
      <p>After restarting the application, there should be three new document templates in the “Literatum JATS” category when you
        select “File &gt; New…” from the menu (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-04-install"/>).</p>
      <fig id="fig-04-install">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <title>New document templates: Issue XML, Literatum JATS article, and submission manifest</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="img/04-install-new.jpg"/>
      </fig>
      <p>If you create a new article with the Literatum_JATS_article template, you will notice the <monospace>&lt;?xml-model
          …?&gt;</monospace> processing instruction right below the XML declaration (<xref ref-type="fig"
          rid="fig-05-article-template"/>). This will force the Schematron to be applied. However, this should not be necessary 
        any more because proper document associations seem to be in place &amp; take care of automatic validation. Press Shift-Ctrl-v or the
        validation button to get a list of validation messages. If you see the messages doubled, remove the xml-model line. 
        Please note that the article template does not pass all
        Schematron tests. It need to be completed according to the validation messages.</p>
      <fig id="fig-05-article-template">
        <label>Figure 5</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Literatum JATS article template</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="img/05-article-template.jpg"/>
      </fig>
      <p>You also need to fill in the issue template (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-06-issue-template"/>) according to the
        instructions and the Schematron messages.</p>
      <fig id="fig-06-issue-template">
        <label>Figure 6</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Issue XML template</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="img/06-issue-template.jpg"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Create the issue workspace in an arbitrary directory. Name the directories within the workspace according to 
      the publisher’s and Atypon’s specifications. The name of the issue directory must match what comes after the slash
      in the manifest’s group-doi attribute. Place manifest.xml alongside the issue directory. By “issue
      directory” we mean <monospace>apf.2017.1000.issue-1</monospace> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-07-directory-layout"/>, not
        the directory <monospace>issue-files</monospace> within that issue directory. 
      </p>
      <fig id="fig-07-directory-layout">
        <label>Figure 7</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Directory layout</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="img/07-directory-layout.jpg"/>
      </fig>
      <p>When you are done preparing the content, you may select the transformation scenario named “build issue” (<xref rid="fig-08-build-issue" ref-type="fig"/>).
        It will run
      for several seconds, depending on the size of your issue directory. It will perform DTD and Schematron validations of all 
      contained XML files. In addition, it will check the directory structure, compliance with the naming conventions, and
      the presence of referenced files, such as graphics.</p>
      <fig id="fig-08-build-issue">
        <label>Figure 8</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Applying the “build issue” transformation</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="img/08-transform-manifest.jpg"/>
      </fig>
      <p>Please note: In the resulting zip file, graphic files will be put in a distinct directory,
          <monospace>graphic</monospace>, for each article. When editing and correcting the articles in the issue directory,
        however, all images are in the same directory as the XML file. This is ok. Even if you happen to know Atypon’s
        submission guidelines, don’t try to anticipate the future directory layout of the zip file. The buid script will take
        care of moving the graphic files to their final destination. This deferred approach allows you to enjoy properly
      linked images while editing the article.</p>
      
      <p>After the package building has been completed, your browser should display the resulting report, as depicted in <xref rid="fig-09-report" ref-type="fig"/>.
      Even if you didn’t include the Schematron xml-model processing instruction of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-05-article-template"/>,
      all the Schematron checks will be performed on the contained articles. In order to deal with the issues in a more friendly 
      environment, you should insert the xml-model processing instruction into your article (copy it from a newly created article)
      and act on the messages in oXygen. </p>
      <fig id="fig-09-report">
        <label>Figure 9</label>
        <caption>
          <title>Package validation report</title>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="img/09-package-report.jpg"/>
      </fig>
      <p>We cannot guarantee that the messages make sense in each and every case. Please ask your contacts at the publisher for assistance,
      or provide them with your valuable feedback.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Extending the Framework</title>
      <p>Local developers may wish to do any or all of the following, extending the customization that this Literatum JATS framework already contains:<list>
          <list-item>
            <p>Rewrite the parameter setting in the HTML Transformation Scenario to point to a local (customized) CSS.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Provide transformation scenarios for any of the JATS Preview transformations or production pipelines given in the
              package, or for customized transformations.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Provide templates using the JATS DTDs supporting OASIS tables instead of or in addition to the templates
              here.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list></p>
      <p>In addition, there are many enhancements possible to this framework, including (but not limited to)<list>
          <list-item>
            <p>More and better CSS.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>Custom actions, tools and buttons in oXygen for operations useful in writing and editing JATS documents, such as
              graphics, list and table support.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>If you make such extensions, please consider sharing them with the community!</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="bib-lctg">
        <mixed-citation><institution>Atypon, Inc.</institution>: <source>Literatum Content Tagging Guide</source> <comment>[URL unknown]</comment></mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
